Guide to the The Tenth Muse records, 1969-1974 and undated, bulk 1973 RL.11073
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
The Tenth Muse records
1969-1974 and undated, bulk 1973
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Tenth Muse (Firm)
Newman, Julia
Berenson, Betty
RL.11073
0.8 Linear Feet
Collection comprises primarily invoices and book claims and requests, along with correspondence, company balance sheets, flyers, booklists, and catalogs, literary proposals and prospectuses, and other printed and manuscript materials related to the bookselling and publishing activities of The Tenth Muse. Much of the material is routine in nature and documents day-to-day work. Includes a folder of letters to and from Isabel Fraire, along with partial translations from the Spanish of her poems. Also contains letters or other material from poets and authors Bill Bissett, Robert Duncan, Tom Clark, and Tom Pickard. There is a copy of Lynn Lonidier’s manuscript for the second part of “A Lesbian Estate.” Among the catalogs is a Shameless Hussy Press catalog, with a handwritten note from poet and publisher Alta Gerrey on the front cover, as well as two 20-page copies of Ganglia Press Index, 1972, compiled by B. P. Nichol, with handwritten comments. Many items feature handwritten dates and notes.
Biographical / Historical
The Tenth Muse was a mail-order bookseller and press in San Francisco, specializing in modern literature and small press publication. It was founded by Julia Newman in the late 1960s. She was assisted by her companion, photographer Sara Betty Berenson. The poet Robert Duncan was a small financial partner in the enterprise. The Tenth Muse closed in the mid-1970s.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Tenth Muse records, 1969-1974 and undated, were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2013.
Collection Overview
Collection comprises primarily invoices and book claims and requests, along with correspondence, company balance sheets, flyers, booklists, and catalogs, literary proposals and prospectuses, and other printed and manuscript materials related to the bookselling and publishing activities of The Tenth Muse. Much of the material is routine in nature and documents day-to-day work. Includes a folder of letters to and from Isabel Fraire, along with partial translations from the Spanish of her poems. Also contains letters or other material from poets and authors Bill Bissett, Robert Duncan, Tom Clark, and Tom Pickard. There is a copy of Lynn Lonidier’s manuscript for the second part of “A Lesbian Estate.” Among the catalogs is a Shameless Hussy Press catalog, with a handwritten note from poet and publisher Alta Gerrey on the front cover, as well as two 20-page copies of Ganglia Press Index, 1972, compiled by B. P. Nichol, with handwritten comments. Many items feature handwritten dates and notes.
Booksellers and bookselling -- United States; Booksellers and bookselling -- California -- San Francisco; Women in the book industries and trade -- United States; Tenth Muse (Firm); Newman, Julia; Berenson, Betty; Bissett, Bill, 1939-; Clark, Tom, 1941-; Duncan, Robert, 1919-1988; Fraire, Isabel, 1934-; Fraire, Isabel, 1934- -- Translations into English.; Lonidier, Lynn; Pickard, Tom, 1946-
- Business information, 1969-1973 and undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Incoming invoices and claims, 1969-1971 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Incoming invoices and claims, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Incoming invoices and claims, 1973 January-February (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Incoming invoices and claims, 1973 March-April (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Incoming invoices and claims, 1973 May-June (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Incoming invoices and claims, 1973 July-November, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Incoming invoices and claims, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Outgoing invoices and claims, 1969, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Utility statements and bank receipts, 1972-1974; bulk1973 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Publisher catalogs and lists, flyers, 1972-1973 and undated; 1 of 2 Files (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Publisher catalogs and lists, flyers, 1972-1973 and undated; 2 of 2 Files (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1970-1973 and undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Correspondence: Isabel Fraire, 1971-1973 and undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Correspondence: Lynn Londier, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Correspondence: COSMEP, 1973 and undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Correspondence: Coxco, 1973 and undated (Box 2, Folder 9)